Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Ronald B. Kaatz Papers, 1915-1996 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Ronald B. Kaatz papers 1915-1996 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company.
3.35 linear feet Extent: 2500 Items
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Ronald B. Kaatz was a network broadcast supervisor, Media Director and Senior Vice President at JWT's Chicago office, where he specialized in cable television advertising. The Ronald B. Kaatz Papers cover the years 1915-1996, with the bulk of materials dating from the 1970s to the 1990s, roughly the period during which Kaatz worked in the media department at the J. Walter Thompson (JWT) Chicago office. The collection consists of research materials, clippings, presentations and slides related to media research and planning, television viewers and advertising. The collection also includes some memoranda and correspondence from other JWT employees; materials from Kaatz's teaching at Northwestern University; and programs from various meetings of television and advertising professionals. Topics addressed include various advertising media--out-of-home (outdoor), Business-to-business (industrial), radio, direct mail, print, and television (broadcast and cable)--as well as marketing to youth, ethnic, and gay consumers. Companies represented in the collection include S.C. Johnson (Johnson Wax), Kraft, Sears, the Partnership for a Drug-Free America, and the Magazine Publishers Association. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
RL.00719
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ronald B. Kaatz Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1996.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1934 Apr. 27 Born, Kansas City, Mo.
1956 B.S., Northwestern University
1957 M.S., Advertising, Medill School of Journalism, Northwestern University
1957-1958 Military service, U.S. Army
1958-1964 Media Research Director, Leo Burnett Company, Chicago
1964-1967 Director of Sales Administration, CBS Chicago office
1967-1980 Vice President, Network Broadcast Supervisor, JWT Chicago
1980 Senior Vice President, Director of Media Resources and Research, JWT Chicago
1982 Publication of book, Cable: An Advertiser's Guide to the New Electronic Media
1984 Director of Media Concepts, JWT
1985 Publication of book, Cable Advertiser's Handbook
1986-1996 Faculty, Integrated Marketing Communications program, Medill School of Journalism, Northwestern University
1989 Publication of book, Advertising & Marketing Checklists; 2nd edition 1995
1991 Publication of book, Media and Space II (Sweden)
1997 Feb. Died
Kaatz was considered an expert in cable television advertising and contributed to multiproduct television specials for Kraft, Inc. He was also founding director of Museum of Broadcast Communications in Chicago.
Collection Overview
The Ronald B. Kaatz Papers cover the years 1915-1996, with the bulk of materials dating from the 1970s to the 1990s, roughly the period during which Kaatz worked in the media department at the J. Walter Thompson (JWT) Chicago office. The collection consists of research materials, clippings, presentations and slides related to media research and planning, television viewers and advertising. The collection also includes some memoranda and correspondence from other JWT employees; materials from Kaatz's teaching at Northwestern University; and programs from various meetings of television and advertising professionals. Topics addressed include various advertising media--out-of-home (outdoor), Business-to-business (industrial), radio, direct mail, print, and television (broadcast and cable)--as well as marketing to youth, ethnic, and gay consumers. Companies represented in the collection include S.C. Johnson (Johnson Wax), Kraft, Sears, the Partnership for a Drug-Free America, and the Magazine Publishers Association.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series: Factbooks, Meetings, Printed Materials, Slides, Subject Files, Writings and Speeches and Oversize Materials. The Factbooks Series includes the contents of binders of assorted correspondence and information on media research collected by Kaatz. The Meetings Series includes program booklets, presentation notes and news clippings related to meetings and conferences of advertising and television professionals. The Printed Materials Series includes pamphlets and brochures relating to advertising research and information on various media formats. The Subject Files Series includes slides that accompanied presentations on television and advertising research, as well as slides of print and billboard advertisements. The Writings and Speeches Series includes scripts of presentations and speeches, primarily given by Ronald Kaatz for JWT meetings, meetings of advertising and television professionals, and for other special events. The Oversize Materials Series includes large format items separated from previous series.
Subject Headings
J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Chicago Office; Kaatz, Ronald B.; Northwestern University (Evanston, Ill.) -- Faculty; Johnson Wax; Kraft Foods Company; Magazine Publishers Association; Partnership for a Drug-Free America; Sears, Roebuck and Company; Advertising, Direct-mail -- United States; Advertising, Industrial; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising media planning; Cable television advertising -- United States; Gay consumers -- United States; Radio advertising -- United States; Television advertising -- Awards; Television advertising -- United States; Young consumers -- United States; Clippings; Slides; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives:
Chicago Office. Non-Proprietary Research Reports
Eleanor Newman Papers
Additional related material may be located in
Kensinger Jones Papers
Sheldon B. Sosna Papers
John Benjamin Harris Papers
Contents of Collection
- Factbooks, 1962-1986, 3 boxes
  Contains booklets of press releases, distribution lists, clippings, brochures, market research reports, media reports, JWT employee memoranda and correspondence primarily related to related to media cost increases, effectiveness of various media formats, and audience research. Items arrived in numbered binders. Original order was maintained.
  - I-III, 1962-1986, (9 folders) (Box 1)
  - IV-VI, 1963-1981, (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - VII-IX, 1969-1986, (8 folders) (Box 3)
- Meetings, 1965-1995, 5 boxes
  Includes program booklets, presentation notes and news clippings related to meetings and conferences of advertising and television professionals. Original folder titles were maintained and items arranged alphabetically by event title.
  - Ad Age (Box 4)
    - Brand Building Conference, 1994 Oct. 6 (Box 4)
    - Creative Workshop on Infomercials, 1982 Aug. 25 (Box 4)
    - Workshop, 1974 Dec. (Box 4)
    - Workshop, 1975 Dec. 4 (Box 4)
    - Workshop on Television Research, 1977 Aug. (Box 4)
  - Advertising Principles, session II, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Advertising Research Foundation
    - Annual conference, 1981 Feb. (Box 4)
    - Annual mid-year conference, 1980 June (Box 4)
    - Effective Frequency Day, 1994 Nov. 2 (Box 4)
    - Electronic Media Research Techniques, 1985 Dec. 12 (Box 4)
    - Electronic Media Workshop, 1988 Dec. 6 (Box 4)
    - Fall conference, 1986 Nov. 3-4 (Box 4)
    - Mid-year conference, 1982 Sept. 16 (Box 4)
    - VCR meeting, 1988 June 16-17 (Box 4)
  - Agate Club of Chicago, 1981 Oct. (Box 4)
  - American Academy of Advertising
    - 1975 Apr. (Box 4)
    - 1994 Apr. 8-11 (Box 4)
  - American Association of Advertising Agencies Media Seminar, 1976 Feb. (Box 5)
  - American Association of Newspaper Representatives, 1970 Mar. 10 (Box 5)
  - American Marketing Association
    - Media Research Panel, 1965 Jan. (Box 5)
    - Seminar, 1995 June 1 (Box 5)
  - Association of Canadian Advertisers, Inc., Communicating Creatively Seminar, 1987 Apr. (Box 5)
  - Association of National Advertisers
    - Television Forum, 1992 Feb. 11-12 (Box 5)
    - Television Workshop
      - Feeling at Home with Video, 1987 Feb. 24 (Box 5)
      - Zapping the Hundredth Monkey, 1986 Feb. 25 (Box 5)
    - Workshop, I's Have It, 1978 Apr. (Box 5)
  - Audiovisual Conference, 1983 July 12 (Box 5)
  - B.P.A. Conference
    - 1988 May 25 (Box 5)
    - 1993 May 12 (Box 5)
  - Beatrice Advertising Seminar, 1984 Nov. (Box 5)
  - Broadcast Advertising Club Seminar, 1983 May 5 (Box 5)
  - Brown Bag JWT meeting, 1970 Oct. (Box 5)
  - Business Week Seminar, 1995 June 20 (Box 5)
  - C.A.B. seminars, 27 Cable Cases in 22 Minutes, 1982 Sept. 29 (Box 6)
  - C.W.O. & O. seminar, 1975 Oct. (Box 6)
  - Cable Television Advertising Bureau, 1982 Feb. 8-9 (Box 6)
  - Canadian Media Director's Council annual seminar, 1973 May (Box 6)
  - Chi Ad Club media seminar, 1989 Mar. 8 (Box 6)
  - Chicago Federated Advertising Club Advertising Workshop, Research Tools of Media Planning, 1964 Oct. (Box 6)
  - Chicago Sun-Times/Daily News Seminar, 1973 Sept. (Box 6)
  - Common Sense and Creativity Media Symposium, 1986 Aug. 7 (Box 6)
  - Communicating Creatively, generic, 1987 Apr. (Box 6)
  - Creactivity, Regional Conference on Creative Communications, 1980 Nov. 21-22 (Box 6)
  - Dart-Kraft Meeting
    - Impact of Change in a Changing Media Environment, 1984 Aug. (Box 6)
    - New Electronic Media, 1981 Oct. 29 (Box 6)
  - First International Media Forum, 1987 Sept. 22-23 (Box 6)
  - Footwear Industries of America, 1988 Apr. 24 (Box 6)
  - Gerber Executive Committee meeting, 1983 Jan. 17 (Box 6)
  - Hill & Knowlton Presents Cutting Through the Clutter, 1986 Apr. 30 (Box 6)
  - International Newspaper Promotion Managers Association, Central Regional Conference, 1973 Oct. (Box 6)
  - JWT Asia-Pacific Media Forum, 1985 June (Box 6)
  - JWT Cable News Seminar, 1973 Apr. (Box 6)
  - JWT Training-Ideas Meeting, 1992 Nov. 20 (Box 7)
  - Kellogg European Management Meeting, 1986 Sept. 10 (Box 7)
  - Marketing & Media Week, 1985 Aug. 13-15 (Box 7)
  - Media Options, 1994-1995 (Box 7)
  - Media Research Directors Association, 1988 Apr. 20 (Box 7)
  - National Media Congress, 1989 Jan. 23 (Box 7)
  - People Approach to Media Planning, 1985 Oct. (Box 7)
  - Promotion Marketing Association Panel, 1992 Mar. 3-4 (Box 7)
  - Publicity Club of Chicago, 1993 Nov. 16 (Box 7)
  - Retail Aid Conference Luncheon, Effective Media Strategy, 1987 Oct. (Box 7)
  - Seminar for Southland, 1987 Dec. 7-9 (Box 7)
  - Traffic Audit Bureau, 1988 Mar. 19-24 (Box 7)
- Printed Material 1962-1989 and undated, 2 boxes
  Contains pamphlets and brochures relating to advertising research and information on various media formats. Includes Nielson Reports of television viewing. Items arrived unfoldered and were grouped by subject and arranged alphabetically.
  - Broadcast Ratings, 1978-1987 (Box 7)
  - Channel switching, 1983 (Box 7)
  - Dictionary of Media Terminology, 1962 (Box 7)
  - Dictionary of Media Terminology, 1962 (Box 8)
  - Magazine research, 1967-1982 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous subjects, 1970-1989 (Box 8)
  - Prime Time Television Communication, 1973 (Box 8)
  - Radio, 1966 and undated (Box 8)
  - Television, 1971-1985, (2 folders) (Box 8)
- Slides, 1977-1989 and undated, 1 box
  Contains slides that accompanied presentations on television and advertising research, as well as slides of print and billboard advertisements. Clients represented include Benetton, Campbell's, Club Med, Coke, Combat, Dewar's, Evian, Fancy Feast, Kentucky Fried Chicken, King Cobra, Kodak, Jiffy Lube, McDonald's, Pizza Hut, San Diego Zoo, Taco Bell, Wendy's and United Airlines. Original folder titles were maintained where available. Items arriving in unlabeled folders were grouped into presentations and advertising slides and arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Cable Advertising Directory, 1977, 1981 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Cable Encyclopedia, 1981-1989 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous outdoor advertisements, 1986-1988 and undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous presentations, 1986-1989 and undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous proofs, 1988-1989 and undated (Box 9)
- Subject Files, 1915-1996 and undated, 10 boxes
  Contains research materials, clippings, research notes and correspondence related to various topics related to Kaatz's teaching and advertising work, with the bulk of materials dating from the mid-1990s. Includes materials related to demographics of television viewers. Original folder titles were maintained and items were arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Airport channel research, 1994 (Box 10)
  - Bates Superstation study, 1981-1982 (Box 10)
  - Broadcast Audience Measurement Services, 1992-1995, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Business to Business, 1990-1993 (Box 10)
  - Cable, 1987-1988 (Box 10)
  - Cinema, 1992-1993 (Box 10)
  - College and youth, 1991-1994, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Commercial zapping, avoidance, clutter, 1984-1994 (Box 10)
  - Commercial zapping, avoidance, clutter, 1984-1994, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Corporate advertising, 1988-1990 (Box 11)
  - Course materials, 1966-1967 (Box 11)
  - Creative media ideas, placements, etc., 1985-1993 (Box 11)
  - Demographics, psychographics, 1991-1993 and undated (Box 11)
  - Direct marketing media, 1990-1995 and undated (Box 11)
  - Effie Awards, 1992-1994 and undated (Box 11)
  - Ethnic, 1992-1995, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Frequency, effective exposure, wearout, 1978-1992 (Box 11)
  - Futures, Delphi, 1993-1994 (Box 11)
  - Gay and lesbian, 1991-1994 (Box 11)
  - Generation X, 1993-1995, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Geodemographics, 1982-1991 (Box 12)
  - Guide to 18 Key Media Terms, 1991 (Box 12)
  - Great Historical Advertising Information, 1915-1974, (3 folders; some items removed to Oversize Materials) (Box 12)
  - History of Media, 1990 and undated (Box 12)
  - Home shopping, 1989-1994 (Box 12)
  - In-store media and promotion, 1991 (Box 12)
  - Industry profiles, 1993-1994 (Box 13)
  - Infomercials and advertorials, 1983-1994 (Box 13)
  - Innovative media research, 1979-1986, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Interactive media, 1993, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Interactive media, 1993, (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - Magazines, 1985-1996, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Magazine Publishers of America, 1990-1991, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Mature market, 1988-1994, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Media information hotline, 1983-1984 (Box 15)
  - Media overviews, cost trends, futures, 1983-1995 (Box 15)
  - Media research, research quality, etc., 1989 (Box 15)
  - Media research basics, 1975-1987 (Box 15)
  - Media research services and sources, 1990-1995 (Box 15)
  - Myers reports, 1990-1994 (Box 15)
  - Network television association, 1991-1993 (Box 15)
  - New media creative ideas, 1981-1988 (Box 15)
  - New media statistics, 1984-1985 (Box 15)
  - New retail media focus, [1990s] (Box 15)
  - Newspapers, 1983-1994 (Box 15)
  - Number Sense, 1989 and undated (Box 15)
  - Original research worldwide, 1984 (Box 16)
  - Out-of-home
    - General, 1979 and undated (Box 16)
    - Out-of-home, supplementary media catalog, 1991 (Box 16)
  - Partnership for a Drug Free America, 1992 and undated (Box 16)
  - Place-based media, 1991-1996 (Box 16)
  - Print audience measurement services, 1983-1995 (Box 16)
  - Product placement, 1994 (Box 16)
  - Public broadcasting, 1987 (Box 16)
  - Public relations, 1991 (Box 16)
  - Radio, 1989-1993, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Recessions and advertising, value of brands, 1990-1993 (Box 17)
  - Research company information, 1985-1993 (Box 17)
  - Research tables, 1979-1982 (Box 17)
  - Return on investment, 1994 (Box 17)
  - Sales promotion, 1991-1994 (Box 17)
  - Small business advertising, undated (Box 17)
  - Specialty advertising, 1991-1993 and undated (Box 17)
  - Sports, 1989-1995, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Spot television and syndication, negotiating, 1978-1994 (Box 17)
  - Stop accidents campaign radio kit, 1965 (Box 17)
  - Subliminal advertising, 1989-1991 and undated (Some items removed to Oversize Materials.) (Box 17)
  - T-shirt advertising, 1994-1995 (Box 17)
  - Television (Box 18)
    - Historical television data, 1954-1978, (5 folders) (Box 18)
    - Television commercial lengths, 1986-1990 (Box 18)
    - Television controversy, boycotts, etc., 1989-1994 (Box 18)
    - Television effectiveness, 1981-1995 (Box 18)
    - Television specials (Box 19)
      - General, 1986-1994 (Box 19)
      - How to Create Superior Value for Sears Advertising, 1986 (Box 19)
      - Kraft television specials, 1981-1986 (Box 19)
  - Test markets and testing, undated, (2 folders) (Box 19)
  - Tobacco advertising, 1990 (Box 19)
  - V.C.R., 1985-1990 (Box 19)
  - Working women, 1985-1993 (Box 19)
  - Yellow pages, 1992 (Box 19)
- Writings and Speeches 1964-1986 and undated, 2 boxes
  Contains scripts of presentations and speeches, primarily given by Ronald Kaatz for JWT meetings, meetings of advertising and television professionals, and for other special events. Includes some speeches given by other JWT executives. Items were arranged alphabetically by folder title. Where several versions of the same speech appeared, items were arranged by date of presentation. Where speech titles were not available, the title of the event was used as the folder title.
  - Agency Perspective at 32,000 Feet, Electronic Media Rating Council, 1984 Jan. 23-25 (Box 20)
  - Broadcast Research, Radio-TV Sales Management Seminar, 1971 (Box 20)
  - Cable: Its Role in Advertising, 20th Century Fox presentation, 1984 June (Box 20)
  - Cable's Creative Communications, 1983 May 3 (Box 20)
  - Changing Communications Opportunities
    - Marketing Environment,Northern Trust Meeting, 1983 June 29 (Box 20)
    - Consumer Environment Life Insurance Advanced Seminar, 1983 Sept. 21 (Box 20)
    - Insurance Industry Consumer Affairs Exchange Conference, 1983 Sept. 22 (Box 20)
    - Newhouse School of Public Communications, 1983 Nov. 18 (Box 20)
  - Christmas Comes Early in a Little Black Box, 1967 Dec. (Box 20)
  - Commentary About Infomercials, Chicago Women in Cable, 1983 Sept. 29 (Box 20)
  - Communications World of the 1980s, 1975 Dec. 5 (Box 20)
  - Creativity with Cable
    - European Media Directors Conference, 1984 Sept. 14 (Box 20)
    - Philadelphia Area Ford Dealers Media Seminar, 1983 Nov. 17 (Box 20)
  - Eleven Questions, Kemper Advisory Board, 1978 (Box 20)
  - From Madison Avenue to Main Street in the 1980s, Variety, 75th Wrap-Up Edition, 1980 Dec. (Box 20)
  - Getting More Ad Dollars for Country, Music Industry Professional Seminar on Country Radio, 1984 Mar. 1 (Box 20)
  - Impact of Change in Today's Changing Media Environment
    - Northwestern University Media Symposium, 1985 June 27 (Box 20)
    - Taft officers and management meeting, 1985 Oct. 8 (Box 20)
  - Increasing Media Effectiveness, National Conference on Broadcast Ministries, 1985 Apr. 23 (Box 20)
  - Innovation and Change, 1977 July 1 (Box 20)
  - Magazine Audience Analysis, 1976 (Box 20)
  - Media Buying and Planning from A to Z '63, Serving Advertising in the Midwest magazine, 1973 Sept. 14 (Box 20)
  - Media Connections
    - Security Analysis meeting, 1985 June 18 (Box 20)
    - S.C. Johnson presentation, 1986 Jan. 17 (Box 20)
    - Undated presentation (Box 20)
  - Media Costs and Current State of Network Television, 1975 Apr. (Box 20)
  - Medium is the Message, Chicago Home Economists in Business, 1984 Oct. 27 (Box 20)
  - National Association of Advertising Publishers, Playboy Club, 1973 Sept. (Box 20)
  - National Broadcasting Company, Radio Affiliates' Panel, 1979 Jan. (Box 20)
  - New Communications Opportunities, Society of Consumer Affairs Professionals, 1983 Apr. 28 (Box 20)
  - New Electronic Media Project, various slide presentations and scripts, undated (Box 20)
  - New Media in the Creative Eye, International Creative Forum, 1981 Nov. (Box 21)
  - New Media, Old Media, Ad Age Yearbook, 1981 Aug. (Box 21)
  - New Media: Reaching the New Customer, Retail Advertising Conference, 1983 Jan. 29 (Box 21)
  - New Media Responders of the 80s, 1981 May 18-21 (Box 21)
  - Outdoorsman's Guide to Cable, Outdoor Advertising Association of America, 1983 Apr. 23 (Box 21)
  - Radio…and Today's Listener, Seven-Up presentation, 1975 (Box 21)
  - Research in the Creative Eye, Junior Women's Advertising Club, 1964 Jan. (Box 21)
  - Review of Media/Marketing Measurement, 1975 Mar. (Box 21)
  - Roundtable on Media Research, Media Decisions magazine, 1974 Feb. (Box 21)
  - Sandoz National Ag Poll, 1993 (Box 21)
  - Selling Newspapers in the 70s, Retail and General Advertising Managers Workshop Conference, Illinois Daily Newspaper Markets, 1970 Apr. 8-10 (Box 21)
  - Skokie: The New Global Village, Skokie Chamber of Commerce, 1981 Oct. (Box 21)
  - Solving Problems in New Ways, Canadian Advertising Research Foundation, 1985 Jan. 31 (Box 21)
  - Technology and the Tribune Company, Tribune Company Advertising Telecommunication Workshop, 1986 Feb. 26 (Box 21)
  - Timetable for the Electronic Revolution, Direct Mail Marketing Association, 1982 Nov. 2 (Box 21)
  - Various speeches and articles, 1981-1984, (4 folders) (Box 21)
  - Viewpoints, TV-Radio Age article, 1975 Oct. (Box 21)
  - What the Ratings Aren't Telling Us, Media Research Club of Chicago, 1984 Sept. 18 (Box 21)
  - Women's Ad Club, 1970 May (Box 21)
  - You Can Do It Yourself, Marketing and Media Decisions, 1982 Apr. (Box 21)
- Oversize Materials, 1915-1991, 1 box
  Contains large format items separated from previous series.
  - Great Historical Ad Information, 1915-1974, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Subliminal advertising, 1989-1991 (Box 22)